<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reflections upon Mr. Varillas his History of heresy Book 1, Tome 1, as far as it relates to English matters, more especially those of Wicliff.</title>
            <author>Hannes, Edward, Sir, d. 1710.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B23911</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19356064</idno>
  <idno type="VID">205509</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240876522</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing H658</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">19356064</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B23911)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 205509)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1672:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reflections upon Mr. Varillas his History of heresy Book 1, Tome 1, as far as it relates to English matters, more especially those of Wicliff.</title>
                  <author>Hannes, Edward, Sir, d. 1710.</author>
                  <author>King, William, 1663-1712.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amstersdam? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"By Edward Hannes, assisted by William King, LLD"--Halkett and Laing.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 72.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Error in paging: p. 42 misnumbered 24.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Varillas, --  Monsieur --  (Antoine), 1624-1696. --  Histoire de l'héresie.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Wycliffe, John, d. 1384.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Reformation --  Early movements.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Heresies, Christian --  History --  Middle Ages, 600-1500.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Church history --  1066-1485.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Brian Matzke </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:205509:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:205509:1"/>
            <p>REFLECTIONS UPON Mr. <hi>VARILLAS</hi> HIS History <hi>of</hi> HERESY. BOOK I. TOME I.</p>
            <p>As far as Relates to <hi>ENGLISH MATTERS;</hi> More especially those of WICLIFF.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Cum primum animum ad Scribendum appulit,</l>
               <l>Id sibi negoti credidit solum dari,</l>
               <l>Populo ut placerent, quas fecisset Fabulas.</l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Terent.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:205509:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:205509:2"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>IT having been publickly desired, that those, in whose way it should lye to expose Mr. <hi>Varillas,</hi> would put themselves to the trouble, The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of these Papers was willing to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute his share, in the part concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Wicliff,</hi> having formerly laid to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether some observations conducing to such a design. <hi>Mr. L'arroque</hi> indeed has gone before him in the attempt; but that ingenious Gentleman was not well advis'd to meddle in a strange Countrey, till time had instructed him more fully in the Constitutions and Language of it. Our present Reflecter has made use of the <hi>Amsterdam</hi> Edition, not being able to procure that of <hi>Paris.</hi> He has given Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> all the Law ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable; he has made no advantage of mistakes, which with any reason could be charged upon the <hi>Printer;</hi> He has
<pb facs="tcp:205509:3"/>contradicted nothing without express proof on his side; and in things highly improbable, which seem to have no Foundation in History, unless he can confront them with Positive and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick Testimonies, he lets the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor alone, and suffers the boldness of the Assertion to be its own security. Last of all, he intreats the Readers pardon, if the Language and Expression are without Choice and Ornament; his profest business and necessary occasions not allowing him any such leisure.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:205509:3"/>
            <head>REFLECTIONS UPON Monsieur <hi>VARILLAS.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Enemies of the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as they seem resolv'd never to leave off writing Controversie, and being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed by our Divines; so they are not wanting upon occasion to turn their style, and furnish out matter of Triumph to our Historians. <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> and <hi>Caussin</hi> heretofore, and of late Monsieur <hi>Maimbourg</hi> and Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur <hi>Varillas</hi> have thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves qualified for this kind of em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment. Above the rest, Mr. <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillas</hi> has us'd his Pen with such a partial Extravagance, and with so little regard to Modesty and Truth, that he has not only provok'd the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:205509:4"/>Learned of the Reformed Profession to chastise his impudence in their publick Writings, but has also drawn upon him the scorn and indignation of several Gentlemen of his own Communion; who in a sense of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and common Ingenuity, have taken some pains to lay open the smooth Impostor. Mr. <hi>Hozier,</hi> Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nealogist to the King of <hi>France,</hi> in his Epistle, declares himself to have discover'd in him above 4000 er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours. <hi>Pere Bouhour</hi> in a discourse of his, makes it his business to expose him: Even his old Friend Mr. <hi>Dr.</hi> seems to have forsaken him, and gone over to his Adversary <hi>Bouhour;</hi> from whose original he is now tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slating the Life of St. <hi>Xavier.</hi> To be free, there is almost as many saults in every single page of Mr. <hi>Varillas,</hi> as in a Printers Table of <hi>Errata:</hi> and if the Arch-bishop of <hi>Paris</hi> would do his Duty, he would find himself bound to put a holy censure upon his Pensioner;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:205509:4"/>and as he was lately very forward to compel those of the Religion to a Recantation of their Faith, so he ought here to oblige Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> to an Abjuration of his History: which we now come to consider.</p>
            <div n="1" type="reflection">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>It was then in the year</hi> 1374 <hi>that Heresie began in</hi> England, <hi>by occasion of the Bishoprick of</hi> Winchester. John Wicliff, <hi>Parson of</hi> Enthlerod, <hi>in the Diocess of</hi> Lincoln, <hi>pretended to the said Bishoprick, and thought he had so well taken his measures, that it could not otherwise escape him, than by such an extraordinary accident as humane prudence could not foresee,</hi> pag. 11.] It might be rational to expect that a <hi>French</hi> Historian would have taken a particular care to inform himself about the Chronology of <hi>Edward</hi> the Thirds Reign; a Prince, whose acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>France</hi> above all Countrys has reason to remember: But Monsieur <hi>Varillas</hi> takes leave to be altogether ignorant of it, not doubting perhaps but he should meet with Gentlemen,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:205509:5"/>and Readers that would not be so un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civil as to contradict the first word of an Author. But a plain Englishman, that has been taught to ask for Truth in History, and not to believe a thing, only because another has affirmed it, whatever may be the consequence, and though he is sure to be called <hi>the Rashest of all men,</hi> will however dare to tell him, that it was not <hi>in the year</hi> 1374. <hi>that Heresie began in</hi> England, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For first, <hi>John Wicliff</hi> had published his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and gained a fame by the year 1360.
<note n="*" place="margin">Dr. <hi>James,</hi> in <hi>Wicliffs</hi> life, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Apology.</note> Secondly, he was never <hi>Parson of Enthlerod;</hi> nor is there any such Parish in <hi>the Diocess of Lincoln,</hi> or in the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> Dominions. If he means <hi>Lut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terworth,</hi> he has so disfigured it, that even a <hi>Leicestershire</hi>-man could not know it again. Thirdly, what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs could the Parson of <hi>Lutter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> have upon a Bishoprick that was full, and had been so for several
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:205509:5"/>years before? For if <hi>William of Wickam</hi> was in disgrace, must his Bishoprick be therefore void? Or would <hi>Wicliff</hi> grow discontented for a preferment not vacant, and raise a Heresy because the Bishop would not dye for him? After this, unless it appear, that <hi>Wicliff,</hi> amongst his other measures, had intended to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch my Lord of <hi>Winchester,</hi> it is plain, he had not laid his designs so deep, as Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade us. Fourthly, an Author of equal credit with Mr. <hi>Varillas, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lydore Virgil,</hi> has imputed <hi>Wicliffs</hi> ill humours to the loss of the Bisho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prick of <hi>Worcester.</hi> From whose Latin, <hi>Florimond de Raymond</hi> has falsly translated it; the Bishop of <hi>Wiorn</hi> and <hi>Varillas</hi> more falsly, <hi>Winton.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="reflection">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p> He goes on (in page the 12th.) to give a Character of the Heretick, <hi>That he understood the Theology of the Schools, which he taught publickly in the Ʋniversity of</hi> Oxford, <hi>in quality
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:205509:6"/>of Regius Professour; That that place had commonly been a step to a Bishoprick, That at present</hi> Wicliff <hi>found his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition oppos'd by the Popes Officers, either because they had entertain'd a Suspicion of him, or Favour for another.</hi>] 1. It must be confest, that <hi>Wicliff</hi> might deserve the Title Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> has bestow'd upon him; but 'tis something strange, that he should stand possess'd of a Dignity which was not founded till about 150 years after, by the Magnificence of <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth; before whose time there was no Regius Professour ever heard of in <hi>Oxford.</hi> In the Paragraph be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> made <hi>Wicliff</hi> so vain as to desire an impossibility, and in this he has put him in real possession of one. 2. The <hi>Popes Officers,</hi> and what follows, Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> will lay no great stress upon, as being only a flourish inserted by a Figure of the modern Rhetorick, which the Wits have call'd Banter.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:205509:6"/>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="reflection">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p> We are told, that <hi>Wicliff thus disappointed, resolves to revenge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self upon the Holy See: In expectation of a fit opportunity he sets himself to read the Schismatical Books of such as had defended the Emperours and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>popes, against the Popes. His first advance was, the maintaining, That the</hi> English <hi>were not bound in Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the payment of Peter-pence, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by King</hi> John <hi>to Pope</hi> Innocent <hi>the Third,</hi> p. 13.] 1. It may be observed, that <hi>Wicliff</hi> was a man of a very ill temper, to ground all his dislike and aversion to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> upon an affront, which we have prov'd it impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible for him ever to have receiv'd. 2. It shall be own'd, that he was ever a profest admirer of <hi>Grosthead</hi> the famous Bishop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> of <hi>Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam</hi> and <hi>Bradwardin;</hi> that had lately flourish't in <hi>Merton</hi> College, where he himself had part of his Education: To accuse him of having read these and such-like writers, had indeed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:205509:7"/>been a proper objection in the mouth of an <hi>Italian;</hi> But, I admire that an Author who had a pension from the same Master with the Marquiss <hi>de Lavardin,</hi> should so far forget himself, as to call those Doctors Schismatical, who stood up for the Civil Rights of Princes, against the encroachments of his Holiness. The whole Collection of <hi>Goldastus</hi> may be read in <hi>France,</hi> and an <hi>English</hi> Historian, whom <hi>Varillas</hi> has reason to know, is said to have been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded for writing in the behalf of that cause, the defenders of which <hi>Wicliff</hi> must not be allow'd to peruse without a crime. 3. I find Mr. <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillas</hi> is much enamoured on the History of the Peter-pence: This is the great Epoche, from whence he has decreed the Historians of the <hi>English</hi> Reformation ought to have started. At present he is much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens'd against <hi>Wicliff</hi> for advising the people not to pay them, and asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that they might with a safe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:205509:7"/>Conscience obey their Prince, who in the year 1364. had prohibited their payment, and left <hi>Wicliff</hi> nothing to do in 1374. but to magnify the action. 4. We intreat, with Dr. <hi>B.</hi> that if ever Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> shall have any farther use of the Peter-pence, he would ascribe their Original to King <hi>Ina,</hi> since they were not first given away by King <hi>John,</hi> nor received first by the Pope, whose name, as Mr. <hi>Pulton</hi> thinks, is so hard to be remembred.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="reflection">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>He says that in</hi> 1374. <hi>the Duke of</hi> Lancaster, <hi>upon having heard</hi> Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liff <hi>Preach, became his Convert, hoping by his Doctrine to support his own inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest; He was then the eldest of King</hi> Edward <hi>the Third's Sons; but had not been so always: The Prince of</hi> Wales <hi>was born afore him; but he was dead; having left but one Son, so young, that the Duke suppos'd it not impossible to exclude him from the Crown. He found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Ambition upon this, that the right of Representation was not clearly enough
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:205509:8"/>made out in the Laws which</hi> William <hi>the Conquerour had given to</hi> England: <hi>so he hop'd to get over the House of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, by encouraging a party against the Clergy, whom they had always hated,</hi> p. 14, 15, 16.] First of all, the Duke of <hi>Lancaster</hi> was not eldest Son to <hi>Edward</hi> III. in the year 1374. for the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> died not till <hi>July</hi> 1376. I could have easily excus'd Mr. <hi>Varillas,</hi> if the falseness of his date had lain only in days or months: But it seems he was resolv'd to kill the Black Prince two years before his time, and it had been for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest of <hi>France</hi> if he could have dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch'd him sooner. 2. Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> has given us a truth, that the Duke of <hi>Lancaster</hi> had not always been the Eldest Son: which is well observ'd of him, for he had Three elder, Two of which Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> has omitted; one of whom left a Daughter, that the Duke ought to have excluded, as well as his Nephew <hi>Richard;</hi> and 'tis not to be doubted, but there had
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:205509:8"/>also been a Plot against <hi>Philippa,</hi> Heiress to the Duke of <hi>Clarence,</hi> had Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> ever heard there had been such a person. 3. The Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Long Robe would desire to know what those Laws are, made by King <hi>William,</hi> in relation to the Succession; and if Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> has any Manuscript of them among his Anecdotes, he is intreated to send it over, and in requital he shall receive from hence two very necessary im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements for a Trader in History, a Play and a Chronicle. 4. In <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> where we pretend no Salique, the Crown descends by the Law of Nature; by which, the whole Right Line takes place of the Collateral, and Nephews are preferr'd to their Uncles. If any of our Kings, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to this Maxim, have posses'd themselves of the Throne, 'tis the respect <hi>Englishmen</hi> bear to a person that has wore the Crown, that keeps them from being severe upon his Memory; but no friend to our Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:205509:9"/>will pretend to justifie the practice. The Tumults rais'd against King <hi>John</hi> only, which have made him esteem'd the most unfortunate of our Princes since the Conquest, are sufficient to testifie, that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ever look'd upon him as an U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surper, and pitied the distress'd <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thur</hi> when they could not serve him. 5. If the Duke of <hi>Lancaster</hi> had any design upon the Crown, he must have been the most impolitick man in the World, to hope for any furtherance of his project, by declaring himself for <hi>Wicliff:</hi> The whole course of our History shews us, that in such cases the contrary Methods have been always taken, and the Clergy have been ever most powerful in altering the Succession. <hi>William Rufus</hi> had the friendship of <hi>Lanfranc; Stephen</hi> was assisted by his Brother <hi>Henry,</hi> Bishop of <hi>Winchester,</hi> and Legate to the Pope. King <hi>John</hi> found a <hi>Hubert</hi> to set the Crown upon his Head. Even the event De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrates,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:205509:9"/>that the Clergy were the persons, by whom the unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate <hi>Richard</hi> must be dethron'd, and the Archbishop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> must carry a strong influence in his Ruine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4 (b)" type="reflection">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <p> After the doubt concerning <hi>the Right of Representation,</hi> Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> makes a short digression cross the Sea into <hi>Bretagn,</hi> whence he brings us a parallel case, where the <hi>English</hi> took part with the Uncle in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of the Neice; <hi>The Eldest Son of the Duke of</hi> Bretagn <hi>died before his Father, leaving but one Daughter, who was afterwards married to</hi> Charles de Blois. <hi>The Youngest Son the Earl of</hi> Montfort <hi>pretended to be heir to the Dutchy,</hi> p. 15.] 1. In this passage Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> has put the <hi>Eldest Son</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of the Second Son, and has made the <hi>Daughter</hi> succeed her Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, when he ought to have said her Uncle: For there is no Herald will deny, but this is the case in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to Genealogy, <hi>Arthur,</hi> Duke of <hi>Bretagn,</hi> by a first venter had two
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:205509:10"/>Sons, <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Guy,</hi> and by a second Marriage, one more, <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort:</hi> Thus he dyed; The elder <hi>John</hi> succeeding; after a time, his Brother <hi>Guy</hi> deceasing, and himself childless, settles the Succession upon <hi>Jane, Guy</hi>'s Daughter: Against this <hi>Jane</hi> it was, after <hi>John</hi>'s death, that <hi>John</hi> Earl of <hi>Montfort</hi> put in his preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions. 2. It is very unreasonable, we see, to expect a good account of Foreign matters from Mr. <hi>Varillas,</hi> when we find him so unpardonably mistaken in his own; and it would be but a vain thing to imagine that writing of the Reformation in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> he should have read Dr. <hi>Burnet;</hi> when quoting a Remark out of the <hi>French</hi> History, he could not afford to consult <hi>Mezeray.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="reflection">
               <head>V.</head>
               <p> One acquainted with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of Mr. <hi>Varillas,</hi> would be apt to wonder, that in five Pages toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there has no Lady appear'd, nor any thing of an Amour: But he can forbear no longer; for p. 16. <hi>The
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:205509:10"/>Kings Mistress</hi> is brought into the Party: <hi>She was a</hi> Spaniard; <hi>by Name</hi> Alex Perez; <hi>who joyn'd her self to the interest of</hi> John <hi>of</hi> Gaunt, <hi>in hopes to be secur'd by him from a Parliament, after the decease of the old King; who by the discourses of her, and the Duke, had begun to think well of</hi> Wicliff, <hi>and would have declar'd himself in favour of Him, but for fear of the Popes.</hi> p. 16, 17.]</p>
               <p n="1">1. Having read that <hi>Wicliff</hi> was a person of great Accomplishments, improv'd by Travel and a large con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation, I began to be afraid that Mr. <hi>Varillas,</hi> who has an Ambition to improve all things into a Love-Intrigue, would have made the King's Mistress have a design of kindness upon him. But finding he had fail'd me there, I began to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>think me who that <hi>Alex Perez</hi> might be, and whether 'twas true, that King <hi>Edward</hi> had fetch'd a Mistress out of the same Country, that Duke <hi>John</hi> had brought his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:205509:11"/>Wife from. But who would suspect that this Court-Beauty, whom <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillas</hi> has dress'd up <hi>a l' Espagnole,</hi> should prove to be no body else but our own <hi>Alse Pierce, English</hi> born and <hi>English</hi> bred.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Our best Historians have left us no remembrance of any concern she ever had with <hi>Church-Affairs;</hi> only 'tis said, indeed, that her first step to the Royal Favour was ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a Dominican; and that thus preferr'd, she did once employ her Interest with the King in behalf of the Bishop of <hi>Winchester;</hi> who had no reason to be thought one of <hi>Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliff's</hi> Friends, if it were true that He, as Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> has before rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, had entertain'd a contrivance to thurst him out of his See. 3. This is certain, King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third had a great esteem for <hi>Wicliff,</hi> so as some have affirm'd he made him his own Chaplain: And to see how the man is mistaken, in saying, the King dissembled the favour he had for him,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:205509:11"/>lest the Pope should be displeas'd by it, it will be fit to tell him that the first occasion of <hi>Wicliff</hi>'s rising in the Kings good opinion, was, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he manfully oppos'd the Papal pretences; and that if ever any of our Princes till King <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII. have Asserted themselves from a dread of the Popes, it must be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily allow'd that this King was not much overaw'd by them, in the beginning of whose Reign the
<note place="margin">(a) 5 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3:</note> Religious were forbid to send Money to their Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours beyond Sea; in the middle of whose Reign were Enacted the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Statutes of
<note place="margin">(b) 25 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.</note>
                  <hi>Provisors</hi> and
<note place="margin">(c) 27 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.</note>
                  <hi>Praemunire;</hi> and both confirm'd again by a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of his about ten years after.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="reflection">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>We are next amus'd with the reasons King</hi> Edward <hi>had to be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleas'd with the Papacy: It was by the Popes ill Offices (caus'd by a jealousie they had of the King) that He saw his
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:205509:12"/>pretensions to the Empire Defeated; and among other things,</hi> Guienne <hi>was lost to the</hi> French, <hi>by his not being able to obtain leave from</hi> Rome <hi>for the taking the new Tenths of His Clergy.</hi> pag. 17, 18, 19.] This whole Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph wants but a Translation for its confutation; and Mr. <hi>D.</hi> might have been as effectual as Dr. <hi>B.</hi> We shall dismiss it at present with only one <hi>Remark,</hi> That as never any of our Kings deserv'd better of the Native Clergy of <hi>England</hi> than King <hi>Edward,</hi> so he had no need to ask the Popes leave for Them to be grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to Him: That very year that he apprehended the designs of <hi>Charles</hi> upon <hi>Guienne,</hi> he borrow'd of them great Sums; and the next, He had given Him by them no less than 50000 <hi>l.</hi> to be paid in the same year. And here again he betrays his igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the <hi>English</hi> Policy and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitutions: For the Clergy met in Convocation, have always had the priviledge of taxing themselves, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:205509:12"/>sending for a Foreign consent; which our Author would make us believe was sollicited by King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> in a <hi>Formal Embassy to the Pope;</hi> but what was that Ambassadours Name we must not know; for perhaps Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> has wisely put himself under his old obligation of Secrecy. The credentials of that Embassy will be no where found, unless it be in the company of Cardinal <hi>Bellay</hi>'s invisible Letters, or the Original <hi>Salique</hi> Law. Which Simile I take occasion to mention here the second time, because I'd have Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> to understand, that I am as fond of my notion of the <hi>Salique,</hi> as he is of his <hi>Peter-Pence.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="reflection">
               <head>VII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>We are at length arriv'd to what he calls the depth of the Intrigue, and is really beyond my Fathom: He begins, That before</hi> William the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querer <hi>there were no written Laws in</hi> England; William <hi>made a Collection still remaining, of such of the unwritten Laws as he design'd should be abolisht:
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:205509:13"/>The Laws he left in force, if strictly observ'd, would have subjected</hi> England <hi>to the conditions of a Conquer'd Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; and the goods of the Ecclesiasticks (which by his Laws he had made his own,</hi> p. 2.) <hi>would have preserv'd his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters in a dependance upon him,</hi> p. 19, 20.]</p>
               <p n="1">1. Our Author, who has div'd so deeply into the Cabinets of Princes, and discover'd so many Manuscript Memoires, inaccessable to other Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, is a little unhappy here, in not having heard of our <hi>Saxonlege,</hi> or <hi>Mercenlege,</hi> or <hi>Danelege</hi> of the Laws of King <hi>Ina,</hi> he that gave the never-to-be-forgotten <hi>Peter-pence,</hi> or King <hi>Elfred,</hi> or King <hi>Edward the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessor,</hi> and other our Princes before the Conquest, with which Mr. <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard</hi> has made a shift to fill a Folio.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That Collection he talks of made by <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour, and still remaining, would bear a great price in <hi>England,</hi> if he is willing to part with it, for we could
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:205509:13"/>never yet get the sight of such a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord: We have indeed a work of that Reign, a noble piece of <hi>English</hi> Antiquity, the Doomsday-book, but the subject of that does not answer our Authors Character. 3. That <hi>William</hi> the First affected the name and advantage of a Conquerour, and design'd to use the <hi>English</hi> not as Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects but Slaves, will never be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the most impartial of our Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storians. 4. Least of all will it be allow'd, that that Prince did ever pretend by the right of Conquest to the Revenues of Holy Church; The confirming of which in all its privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges was the first solemn act of his entrance; and the encreasing of it with the Foundation of a goodly Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, was what he chose to be the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and lasting memorial of his Victory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="reflection">
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <p> What follows is so gross and unpardonable, that I shall refer him to be corrected by the Almanack, or the Man that shews the Kings at
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:205509:14"/>
                  <hi>Westminster.</hi> If the Compositor does not step in to relieve the credit of the Author, and bring him out of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience, as he calls it, by taking shame to himself, no man hereafter will endure his Books, but in such a Library as <hi>Don Quixot</hi>'s, or in such a Catalogue as Mr. <hi>Langbanie</hi>'s. He gravely tells us, <hi>That the Two</hi> Stephens <hi>of the House of</hi> Blois, <hi>who succeeded the Sons of</hi> William, <hi>took no care of the unwritten Laws,</hi> &amp;c. Sure he penn'd this passage at a certain season when they say men are us'd to see double: Otherwise, how is it possible for him to make us Two Kings of one Usurp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er? Who ever heard of King <hi>Stephen</hi> the Second of <hi>England?</hi> Who was his Wife? What Children had he? What did he do? Which King of <hi>France</hi> did he beat? Where was he Buried? 'Tis a Miracle that all this should escape the World; and whilst we, the ignorant, thought there ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had been any more than one <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen,</hi> Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> should produce
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:205509:14"/>another. However, it will be hard for him to prevail with the wary Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> amongst the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues Royal erected in the <hi>Exchange,</hi> to raise an Essigies to the memory of the Second King <hi>Stephen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="reflection">
               <head>IX.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>To the</hi> Stephens, he says, <hi>suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded the House of</hi> Anjou; <hi>who were reduc'd to implore the authority of the Holy See, to put them in their possessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of</hi> England: <hi>In them the Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive was weakned, by some reasons no man but</hi> Varillas <hi>would give, and first the Clergy and Nobility, and after that the Populacy getting the ascendant of the Crown, the Parliament took its birth. The power of which, during its Session was so great, as to leave almost no hing but the Title to the King:</hi> Henry <hi>II. was the first that would have shook off the Yoke,</hi> p. 20, 21.] 1. The House of <hi>Anjou</hi> was so formidable in <hi>Maud</hi> and her Son <hi>Henry,</hi> and the People so well dispos'd to receive them, that he had no need of any such assistance from abroad. 2. How
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:205509:15"/>could the House of <hi>Anjou</hi> bring a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentary <hi>Yoke</hi> upon themselves, which <hi>Henry</hi> II. should be the first that endeavour'd to shake off, when before <hi>Henry</hi> II. the House of <hi>Anjou</hi> never reign'd in <hi>England.</hi> 3. 'Tis a shame Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> should know so little of that august Assembly, the Parliament, as to date the rise of it from <hi>Henry</hi> II. whereas at least it ought to have been carried as high as his Grandfather. 4. He may think perhaps to make it amends by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mistake, having falsly rais'd them in their Session so far above the King, as in a manner to annihilate his power for the time. One that reads this in a <hi>French-man,</hi> would think he was discoursing of the Doge of <hi>Genoa;</hi> and not of a Monarch, who, as his present Majesty has been pleas'd publickly to observe, has e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough power by Law to make him as great as he can wish; though he suffers his Parliament to maintain their just priviledges at another rate,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:205509:15"/>than the long-disus'd Estates of a neighbouring Kingdom. And here 'tis probable our Author may think himself safe behind a Quotation fetch'd from <hi>Bologna;</hi> and 'tis likely he will be so: For a Subject of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> will not presume to interpose, because the matter is of so high a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, nor a Prince condescend so low as to take notice of an affront, when the Author is <hi>Varillas.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="reflection">
               <head>X.</head>
               <p> He goes on to tell us, <hi>That</hi> Henry <hi>II. his designs were prevented by</hi> Becket<hi>'s murder; which happen'd by two indiscreet Souldiers, explaining in too great a latitude some words let fall by the King in relation to the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop. So this project was set on foot no more till</hi> Edward <hi>the Third's time, who taking up the same design of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressing the States of Parliament, began with that of the Clergy, which by</hi> Wie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liff<hi>'s proceedings he was in hopes to mortifie,</hi> p. 22.] 1. Those <hi>Two Souldiers</hi> of his were Four Knights, Sir <hi>Hugh Merville,</hi> Sir <hi>William Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:205509:16"/>Sir <hi>Richard Brittain,</hi> and Sir <hi>Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nold Fitz-Ʋrs.</hi> An Historian ought to understand so much Blazon, as to know a Knight from a Souldier; and not to suffer himself to be so much in haste, as to leave half his number behind him: But Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> may think he has done the Gentlemen no wrong, in giving them a name so much admir'd in modern <hi>France;</hi> and I am the more willing to excuse him for being too short in this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, because he allows for it in the Two <hi>Stephens.</hi> 2. He told us in p. 18, 19. <hi>That the reason of King</hi> Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward<hi>'s designs upon the Clergy, was a desire he had of revenging himself upon the Popes, who had done him, as he thought, so many injuries, there recount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed:</hi> But here that resolution is made to proceed from an intent of his, to bring down the power of Parliaments. Now I begin to have some hopes of our Author: For I see he knows him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self so well, as not to rely upon his own relation laid down before; and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:205509:16"/>Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> will not believe Mr. <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillas:</hi> He guesses again; and thinks 'tis here, as in <hi>Arithmetick,</hi> where two false Suppositions may produce a Truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="reflection">
               <head>XI.</head>
               <p> After this long deduction, in which, it seems as though he had been resolv'd to spend at once all the little stock of knowledge he has in the <hi>English</hi> Chronicles, he returns to <hi>Wicliff; who finding himself thus secure, taught openly, that the</hi> English <hi>Lords might resume the goods given by their Ancestors to the Church, that neither Pope nor Bishops might Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate; that Sacraments administred by wicked Priests were ineffectual.</hi> p. 23.] Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> having fram'd to himself a notion, that <hi>Wicliff</hi> was only us'd as a State-Instrument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Clergy, he has accordingly pickt only these out of his many Doctrines, as appearing most proper to serve his <hi>Hypothesis;</hi> as if these three misrepresented Articles, were the only, or the chief Tenets by
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:205509:17"/>which Dr. <hi>Wicliff</hi> grew to be so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable: It was his great esteem for the Holy Scriptures, of which his Translation still remains a memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable instance; his right notion of the blessed <hi>Eucharist,</hi> the opposition he made to the encroaching Mendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants in behalf of the Secular Clergy; not to mention his confess'd Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies in Polemick Divinity and Philosophy, with a strictness of life, which his Acquaintance rever'd; which his Adversaries, amongst all their Accusations, have never pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to call in question; and which engag'd in his favour the major part of the University where he liv'd, and particularly the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour and both the Proctors of the year 1382. It would be too large a work, and not becoming such a Pamphlet as this, to enter into a Desence of that great Man, and all his particular Opinions, and to shew how industrious the Friers have been to blacken him since his Death;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:205509:17"/>when even in his Life time, he was charg'd with the sancies and errours of other Men; which, when in open Court, he declar'd never to have been his; this his Remonstrance, has by some since, been pleasantly term'd a Recantation: For the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, the diligent Dr. <hi>James</hi> may be consulted by the curious, for their farther satisfaction, till some gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Pen shall appear more fully in the Cause of <hi>Wicliff,</hi> and do justice to so eminent a Confessor.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="reflection">
               <head>XII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>He keeps us still in the year</hi> 1374. <hi>and in that it was, as he tells us, that Pope</hi> Gregory XI. <hi>hearing of the Novelty, wrote to the Archbishop of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>and Bishop of</hi> London, <hi>by any means to suppress it. They Cite</hi> Wicliff, <hi>who appears, but in the posture of one that expected a Reward, and not a Punishment. He pleaded, that he had never design'd to alter the Christian Truth; that if any thing offensive had escap'd him, he revok'd it sincerely, and submitted to Pennance
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:205509:18"/>and publick Correction: Ʋpon. this they put into his hands a Billet of the three Errours he had taught; which having explain'd, to their content, there was nothing left for the two Bishops, but to Absolve him, upon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise made never more to maintain in publick any equivocal Propositions.</hi> p. 23, 24.]</p>
               <p>At the first reading this Narration, drawn up with so much seriousness and formality, it would look like confidence to suspect it; and yet upon search, it will be manifest, that 'tis false and sophisticate in almost all its parts. Having made this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral observation, how cautious our Author has been, in avoiding those unlucky things call'd Dates, as not having hitherto specified so much as the Month in which any Adventure fell out; we must not expect he should tell us what was the date of the Popes Bull, of the Episcopal Citation, or the time of <hi>Wicliff</hi>'s appearance; all which would have been look'd for
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:205509:18"/>in an exact History; and if they had here been set down by Mr. <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillas</hi> would have supplied us with matter for a Consutation. 1. All our Annals and Registers place this Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing two years later, about the 19th. of <hi>February,</hi> 1377. 2. That <hi>Wicliff</hi>'s behaviour there, was contrary to what Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> has represented it: I will at present take no other care to demonstrate, than by setting down the words of <hi>Knighton:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>l.</hi> 5.</note>
                  <hi>Cumque die Statuto ad objecta respondere deberet, omnem prejactita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem cordis audaciam sine mora dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sit,</hi> &amp;c. 3. I shall ask of Mr. <hi>Varillas,</hi> whether it be the way of the <hi>French</hi> Law, or any other he has studied, for a Man to plead before his Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be known, and to answer an Accusation, when 'tis not yet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd against him. If <hi>Wicliff</hi> did so, yet this we know, that he made no such set harangue; that after that, he had no such Billet of 3 Articles presented him; that the Exposition
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:205509:19"/>our Author ascribes to him is ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious; and in short, all that follows. For a Tumult happening, the Court was oblig'd to break up abruptly before Nine of the Clock in the Morning; and never came to give such an Absolution, or to receive such a promise. 4. If he had ever read any writer upon the present particular, he could never have made so defective a discourse of it, in which he has not told us so much as that this Trial was at <hi>London;</hi> that the great Duke of <hi>Lancaster,</hi> and <hi>Henry,</hi> Marshal of <hi>England,</hi> appear'd in favour of the Criminal; and finally, the occasion the Bishops found to leave the Court sooner than was intended.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="reflection">
               <head>XIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>We are acquainted, That after this</hi> Wicliff <hi>Relaps'd: The same Pope hearing of it, complain'd of the</hi> English <hi>Prelates, and to shew what they ought to have done, condemn'd the Propositions of</hi> Wicliff <hi>himself: The Prelates being asham'd to be out-done,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:205509:19"/>Assembled themselves at</hi> Canterbury <hi>in the form of a Council, and ponounc'd by the mouth of the Archbishop of the place, who was their Primate an Anathema a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst his Doctrine: And all this in King Edward's Reign, and the year</hi> 1374. p. 25.]</p>
               <p n="1">1. To set him right in his Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nology, this second Convocation is on all hands affirm'd to have fall'n out in the Reign of <hi>Richard</hi> II. which began <hi>June</hi> 21, 1377. 2. Whereas he makes our Bishops so complaisant, as immediately to fall about what the Pope had hinted to them by his example; 'tis evident by the Original Acts still remaining, and to be seen in their proper Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chieves, that he was forc'd to oblige them to it by formal Letters; bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Date from <hi>Rome,</hi> 11 <hi>Cal. Jun. Anno</hi> 7. <hi>Pontificatus;</hi> though not put in Execution till after the Death of King <hi>Edward.</hi> Why does Mr. <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillas</hi> mention nothing of this Bull? or is not the Popes Letter of as great
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:205509:20"/>moment, and as well deserving to be taken notice of, as a Love-Letter or a Lampoon. 3. He is very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy in descending to particulars, and not keeping aloof in generals, and at a due distance: For as in the first Convocation he assigns us no place for their Session, so here he has given us a wrong one, and <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> is many Miles from <hi>Canterbury.</hi> 4. The Bishops met at <hi>Lambeth</hi> were so far from <hi>pronouncing an Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema against</hi> Wicliff<hi>'s Doctrine,</hi> that they found reasons not to give any definitive Sentence; which had they done, it would have appear'd on Register, amongst other Acts we have remaining of the same Council.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="reflection">
               <head>XIV.</head>
               <p> This 1374. has been a very long year, and at last <hi>King</hi> Edward <hi>dies in it;</hi> who, however, I am well satisfied, was in the Throne above two years after. <hi>In his life time he had tenderly lov'd the Duke of</hi> Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, <hi>and had given him outward demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strations, that he would leave him the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:205509:20"/>Crown; nevertheless when he was dead, a Will was found written and sign'd with his Hand, which rendred Justice to the Prince of</hi> Wales, <hi>in the Person of his Son</hi> Richard, <hi>then but</hi> 12 <hi>years old, and declared him Successour, in Exclusion to the Duke of</hi> Lancaster, <hi>and the Dukes of</hi> Gloucester <hi>and</hi> Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge, <hi>his Brothers. The Parliament of</hi> England <hi>approved this VVill,</hi> p. 25, 26.] 1. Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> is the first dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverer of any <hi>Demonstrations</hi> given by <hi>Edward</hi> the III. to the Duke of <hi>Lancaster,</hi> that should put him in hopes of the Crown: On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, <hi>Walsingham</hi> tells us in express words, <hi>Eo tempore, nondum finito Parliamento,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hyp. Neust.</note>
                  <hi>Dominus Edwardus, Princeps Walliae,</hi> 8. <hi>die Julii in die S. Trinitatis defun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitur. Dominus Richardus de Burde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galia, filius Dom. Edw. Principis in hoc Parliamento factus est Comes Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>striae &amp; non multo post Dux Cornubioe, &amp; Princeps Wallioe est creatus. Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardus in festo S. Georgii apud Winde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leshores
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:205509:21"/>contulit Richardo de Burdegel, Haeredi suo, ordinem militarem.</hi> From hence any man of inference, will see what reason the Duke of <hi>Lancaster</hi> had to enlarge his hopes, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise himself that Prince <hi>Richard</hi> was not design'd for the Crown by his Royal Grand-father. 2. Here is a Will produc'd, never known in the World, till Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> printed his History: Nothing of this in any of our Authors, but counterfeited by him, who is one of the first men that ever forg'd a Testament, without hopes of getting by it so much as a Legacy. 'Tis something observable, that he should deal so by a Prince, who is the first in <hi>England,</hi> that has made a Statute about Pillories. 3. A man that goes about a cheat, should not be in haste, but let his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention tarry for his Judgment: This Will is so awkardly contriv'd, that it betrays it self at first sight. The Duke of <hi>Cambridge</hi> (as he calls him) is put after his younger Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:205509:21"/>neither was he ever Duke of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> but Earl only, in which cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter he continued till 1386. when his Nephew created him Duke of <hi>York. Thomas</hi> of <hi>Woodstock,</hi> is yet more beholding to Mr. <hi>Varillas,</hi> for having excluded him by the name of the Duke of <hi>Gloucester;</hi> whereas he had no title when his Father dy'd, nor did he arrive to this Dukedom till the abovenamed year 1386. Now 'tis a pretty hard conceit to suppose, that the King did not know which of his Sons was the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or that he should put by from the Crown two Dukes he had never heard of; or lastly, that prophesying of the future honours of his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, he should guess right about one, and be mistaken about the other. 4. Not to harrass him any more; as for what concerns the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament after the Kings Death, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to know who should call it, if the new King was not yet approv'd, as he is pleas'd to term it. And
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:205509:22"/>about the Act of Approbation, I request of him to tell us where it is to be found, that so it may be put into the next Edition of <hi>Keeble.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="reflection">
               <head>XV.</head>
               <p> He informs us, p. 26, 27. <hi>That the unfortunate</hi> Alix Perez <hi>avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the punishment prepar'd for her, by embarking with what she had most pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious upon a</hi> Flemmish <hi>Vessel, which carryed her to the Coasts of</hi> Galicia. <hi>And the Tutors of the young King for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore to seek after her, either because they thought her below their anger, or that they were perswaded the King of</hi> Castile <hi>would not abandon her to their discretion, because of the Riches which she brought from</hi> England <hi>into</hi> Spain, <hi>or of the pretensions which the Duke of</hi> Lancaster <hi>had upon his Crown.</hi> Thus far our Romancer: His friend <hi>Tacitus</hi> has begun his Annals with a Verse, and Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> improving the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and advancing upon those grounds, has made his whole Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry into a Poem. Had he liv'd in the days of Knight-errantry, he would
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:205509:22"/>certainly have been invited over to the Honourable Employment of Imperial Historiographer in the Court of <hi>Trebizond,</hi> and deserved a Pension extraordinary from his Highness Don <hi>Alphebo.</hi> Having here to do with a Female, he has acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himself extreme civilly, and much like a Gentleman, to re-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct the strange Lady to her own Countrey, with all her Jewels and other her stoln accoutrements. But our rough Historians deal more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindly by her, and tell us, that by a Parliament at <hi>Westminster, Alice Pierce</hi> had all her goods confiscate, and herself banisht, so as really to be left the <hi>Ʋnfortunate Alix Perez.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="reflection">
               <head>XVI.</head>
               <p> We are now coming on to <hi>Tyler</hi>'s Rebellion; and here our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor has given a master-stroke of his fancy, and has found a contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance to draw in <hi>Wicliff</hi> for the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the whole commotion. <hi>Viclof taking advantage of the Kings minority, past on from the Clergy to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:205509:23"/>vent his doctrine against the Lay-No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and Magistracy; and at length came to a conclusion, that there ought to be no inequality in goods, but a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity of all things. Having thus dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd the Peoples minds, he receiv'd into his party one</hi> John Balee, <hi>a man the most turbulent and seditious of all</hi> England: <hi>He was a Priest by profession, and had escap'd out of Prison, where his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary had secur'd him. He fearing to be re-taken, and not having means of subsistance beyond the Seas, found there could be no safety for him without kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dling a Civil War. So having often conferr'd with</hi> Wicliff, <hi>he preach'd and improv'd his opinions, so as to draw after him to the number of</hi> 200000 <hi>persons, pretending to esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish an Equality, but indeed to put himself into the dignities of</hi> Simon de Saberia, <hi>Arch-bishop of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>and Lord Chancellour of</hi> England, p. 27, 28, 29.] 1. I love an Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian of a great Soul and free thoughts, that scorns to be beholding to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:205509:23"/>accounts, and will go no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than himself for his relations: 'Tis an argument of a <hi>Vulgar Spirit</hi> to be content to take up with what is written already, and present the World with nothing that's new. <hi>Wicliff</hi>'s Preaching had no more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to this Rebellion, than the Edition of <hi>Confucius</hi> in <hi>France</hi> had to the Sufferings of the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> or than Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi>'s Conclusions are us'd to have to his Premises. 'Tis well known by all men of Judgment and Reading, that <hi>Wicliff</hi> always de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended Order and Distinction; that he himself took his <hi>Degree of Doctor,</hi> and that his Friends and Patrons were of <hi>the Nobility;</hi> and that all his troubles took their rise from his zeal in maintaining the <hi>Supremacy</hi> of his Prince: So far was he from being Author of this Tumult against him. To pass by our Authors for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfulness, who having (<hi>p.</hi> 12.) brought in <hi>Wicliff,</hi> as designing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but to revenge himself upon
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:205509:24"/>the Popes Officers and the Clergy, for a suppos'd affront receiv'd from them, does here undeservedly, and without reasons assign'd, set him as hotly against the Laicks and Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. All agree, that the Rebellion proceeded from the seeming Opres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, and from the Taxes, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est that had ever been in <hi>England,</hi> thought to be unreasonably impos'd, and insolently exacted in <hi>Kent,</hi> and the neighbouring parts. 2. Now for <hi>John Ball,</hi> the Seditious Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>astick, he was clapt up for tenets of his own; and was so far from ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving escap'd Prison, to go and enter into frequent consults with <hi>Wicliff;</hi> and from thinking it necessary after that, to raise the People of <hi>England</hi> for the securiry of himself, an incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable Curate; that the Peasantry was first up in arms; and amongst their other extravagancies, having broke open the Prisons, they set free with the rest this <hi>John Ball,</hi> who then indeed joyn'd with his Deliverers.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:205509:24"/>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="reflection">
               <head>XVII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Multitude</hi> (he says) <hi>march'd on to the Palace of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop; where forcing entrance, they find the Prelate upon his knees, and with all the circumstances of horrour, cut off his Head. The Troubles were renew'd soon after in the Provinces of</hi> Essex <hi>and</hi> Kent, <hi>and quickly past into those of</hi> Norfole, Suffolc, Erfolc, <hi>and</hi> Cambridge. <hi>Thence the</hi> Wicliffists <hi>advanc'd towards</hi> London <hi>in a body innumerable: They were a charge to no man; they paid for what they had, and punisht with death any that were convicted of having stoln. When they were arriv'd at</hi> Bloquet, <hi>King</hi> Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard <hi>sent to demand the reason of their taking Arms, but receiv'd an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer full of insolence: And when the Mayor would have shut the City-Gates against them, he was hindered by those of the ordinary sort. The Seditious enter</hi> London, <hi>burn the Count of</hi> Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casters <hi>Palace, and throw the goods of the Count into the River: Then they invest the</hi> Tower, <hi>whither the King
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:205509:25"/>and Court had fled for refuge, gain entrance, and murder the Chancellour, the Treasurer, and other Officers, hid in the</hi> Tower, <hi>and several other Churches of</hi> London, p. 29, 30, 31.] 1. I would have been glad if Mr. <hi>Varil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las</hi> would have told us where this <hi>Palace of the Arch-bishop</hi> stood, and whither it was not that at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> near <hi>Candamart?</hi> It is sure, that the Arch-bishop was not massacred in any Palace he had, and before I end this Paragraph, I will undertake that Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> himself shall tell me so. 2. Amongst the <hi>Provinces</hi> concern'd in the Tumults, we meet with <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folc</hi> for one: Mr. <hi>Camden</hi> and Mr. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> knew nothing of such a place; and if Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> will come over hither, and discover where this County lyes, I engage my Honour that at least the Freeholders of it shall chuse him Knight of the Shire. 3. That the Rebels were so exact in paying for what they had, I must beg his pardon if I believe a mistake,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:205509:25"/>not only by their Actings, but also by their Principles, which Mr. <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillas</hi> told us before, were to make <hi>all things common.</hi> But let us follow them to <hi>Bloquet;</hi> which however we cannot do without a guide; for 'tis impossible to find any such place, unless by that name he means to understand <hi>Black-heath,</hi> or <hi>Barnet,</hi> or rather <hi>Mile end</hi> 4. The Mayor not being suffered [<hi>to change the City Locks,</hi> or so much as] <hi>to shut the Gates,</hi> the Peasantry came on, and Plundered the <hi>Earl of Lancasters</hi> house in the <hi>Savoy.</hi> Sure one would think they had depriv'd him of his Dukedome too: for otherwise how comes it to pass that he who has hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto been all along <hi>Le Duc de Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>castre,</hi> should be now on a sudden diminish'd into <hi>Le Conte de Lancastre?</hi> By this figure of <hi>Varillism</hi> it was, that the Lord <hi>Darley</hi> was brought down into a private Gentleman, and the Knights of King <hi>Henry</hi> into Souldiers. If there were nothing
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:205509:26"/>else to be said about the present Rebellion, this single passage were enough to evince the Rebels not to have been the Disciples of <hi>Wicliff;</hi> for if so, this Illustrious Patron of his must needs have met with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther sort of usage at their hands: Tho farther yet it may be noted, that <hi>Jack Straw</hi> in his last confession declared, Their design was to save the <hi>Mendicant</hi> Friers, an Order of men, who had always shew'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves the most violent Enemies to <hi>Wicliff.</hi> 4. We are now come to the business of <hi>Simon de Suberia.</hi> Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> mention'd above, that the <hi>Archbishop</hi> was beheaded in his Palace; and now assures us, That the <hi>Chancellour</hi> is murdered in the Tower, either forgetting what he had told us before (p. 28.) that both those dignities were in one Person, <hi>Sudbury;</hi> or designing to deter peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from Ambition and a desire of Plurality in high Offices, by shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that a man must under go as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:205509:26"/>several deaths as he holds prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and in this example, that the same person was first put to death in his Spiritual capacity of <hi>Archbishop,</hi> and again Massacred some time after for his temporal qualification of <hi>State-Minister:</hi> For that a man may be <hi>two-fold,</hi> was formerly seen, in the Case of <hi>Charles</hi> V. The truth is this, <hi>Sudbury</hi> from the first beginning of these distur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances had follow'd the fortune and person of the King, and was at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent retir'd with him into the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, where the multitude seiz'd and beheaded him. So dyed a Prelate, of whom our Authors have given us a very honourable mention; and yet Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> has been pleas'd to assign him so ill-natur'd and unjust a character, (p. 23. &amp; p. 28, 29.) that one who reads it, would think he had mistaken his Man, and was describing the Heretick <hi>Wicliff,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of <hi>Sudbury</hi> the Legate of the Holy See. 5. Besides the Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:205509:27"/>he tells us more of the Kings Ministers were kill'd in <hi>the Tower and other Churches.</hi> Really Sir, if the <hi>Tower</hi> be a <hi>Church,</hi> it is one of the largest and best fortified Churches in <hi>Europe.</hi> I have so good an opinion of his Friend Mr. <hi>Sorbeir,</hi> as to think that out of the little knowledge of <hi>England</hi> he pickt up here, he could have inform'd our Author, that the Tower is never lookt upon by us as a Cathedral, but as an Arsenal: Whither by this Paper I invite Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> to come over, and see the famous Canons, with which <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII. of Glorious Memory took <hi>Boleign.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="reflection">
               <head>XVIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ʋpon a Pardon proclaim'd, great numbers deserted; but a consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable party still kept together in a Body, under the conduct of</hi> Gauthier Igler, <hi>the most adroit and most reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute person amongst them. After the story of whose death, and some other passages, we find, that</hi> Ball <hi>preach'd at</hi> Seblaker, <hi>to</hi> 20000 <hi>people, upon
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:205509:27"/>whose being seiz'd and executed, the Troubles had an end: At last he says, That</hi> Wicliff <hi>was never present either at the Assemblies of the Seditious, or at the Assassination of the Archbishop of</hi> Canterbury, p. 32, 33, 34.] 1. Our Author would have deserv'd much commendation, and sav'd the Reader a great deal of thinking, had he plac'd a Key at the end of his Book, as we see done in another work of the like natare, call'd <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clays Argenis;</hi> it would have been easie then to have known a proper name under all its disguises, we should then have perceiv'd, that <hi>Haviet</hi> was put for <hi>Wiat; Gauthier Igler</hi> for <hi>Wat Tyler;</hi> and what had been the meaning of the not yet deciphered <hi>Seblaker;</hi> which we can only guess to be <hi>Black-heath.</hi> 2. By this last sentence, which Truth has extorted from Mr. <hi>Varillas,</hi> it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that <hi>Wicliff</hi> was altogether innocent, and that our Author would never have brought him into
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:205509:28"/>this Rebellion, but to gain the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pick of describing it; which <hi>Image</hi> with all its graceful circumstances must otherwise have been lost, for want of an opportunity to introduce it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="reflection">
               <head>XIX.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Schism happening between the Popes,</hi> Wicliff <hi>in the year</hi> 1382. <hi>makes his advantage of it; but his offers being rejected by the Parliament, he found himself obliged to retire into the Province of</hi> Wales, <hi>newly subjected to the</hi> English. <hi>There he attack'd the</hi> Benedictines <hi>by a Writing: Ʋpon this, Archbishop</hi> Courtney <hi>assembles a Council at</hi> London, <hi>soon after</hi> Easter, <hi>where were condemn'd these Propositions of</hi> Wicliff, <hi>That the Substance of the Bread and Wine,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>These Articles thus condemn'd,</hi> Wicliff <hi>himself being cited, made his appearance, where he abjured all he had taught without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception. This Recan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ation they obliged him to put in writing, and recite over again. And this piece had been seen in its place amongst the other Acts of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:205509:28"/>this Council, if the</hi> English <hi>Compiler, too passionate for the Glory of his Nation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Spelman.</note>
                  <hi>or unwilling to give Arms to the</hi> Catholicks <hi>against the Heresie of</hi> Calvin, <hi>of which he made profession, had not suppress'd this retractation, and plac'd instead of it a profession of Faith, which properly speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is nothing but plainly a captious Qualification of the Errours of this Heretick. The last act of the Council was an Ecclesiastick procedure against his three famous Disciples,</hi> Rippendon, Hereford, <hi>and</hi> Aston. p. 36. <hi>ad</hi> p. 42.</p>
               <p n="1">1. What is said in the beginning of this Paragraph, we find no where warranted; nor that <hi>Wicliff</hi> ever was in <hi>Wales:</hi> which our Author makes <hi>newly Conquered</hi> by the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish;</hi> an Expression something im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper for a Countrey, that we had acquir'd no less than a Hundred years before. 2. What he says was Penn'd against the <hi>Benedictines,</hi> I have reasons to believe to have been
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:205509:29"/>no other than the Two Treatises written by <hi>Wicliff,</hi> and in the last Century, printed against the <hi>Mendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants.</hi> 3. 'Tis acknowledged that <hi>Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney</hi> in a Council, call'd upon <hi>May</hi> 17. did condemn several Conclusions, and that the same Archbishop upon <hi>June</hi> 20. sat upon <hi>Hereford, Reppingdon</hi> and <hi>Ayshton,</hi> accus'd of holding those Conclusions: <hi>Ayshton</hi> pleaded apart; The Two other put into the Court a Paper, which the learned Sir <hi>Henry Spelman</hi> has publish'd in his Councils from the MSS. Copy, in the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Registry of the Archbishop of <hi>Canterbary, Nuncupat. Courtney. Fol.</hi> 25. At neither of these conventions, nor at any other time throughout this whole year did <hi>Wicliff</hi> appear at all at <hi>London</hi> before the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop: What assurance then must that Man be Master of, who dares affirm that he made, wrote, recited in this Council a formal Recantation of <hi>all his opinions whatever, without reserve;</hi> whereas there is not so
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:205509:29"/>much as any pretended retraction of his of any kind, that can possibly be brought to concern any more than the single Article about the blessed <hi>Eucharistt?</hi> As for that Accurate and Honoured Collector Sir <hi>H. Spel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> as this is the first time he has ever been accus'd of <hi>Falsifying,</hi> so his confident Accuser could not do it, without giving matter to any exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining Reader of returning the Charge, and Convicting him of his own Calumny. For had this Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riographer of <hi>France</hi> but once vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safed to look into the Book he has pass'd so blind a censure upon, he would easily have found that his <hi>Latin</hi> Friends, who told him of such a palliation in behalf of <hi>Wicliff,</hi> had a little misinform'd him. For such a palliation is so far from being there, that there is nothing that can possibly be thought like it, or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staken for it, unless it be the above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named Paper of <hi>Hereford</hi> and <hi>Rep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pingdon:</hi> Which if he shall please to
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:205509:30"/>doubt of, whether it be Authentick or no, upon his acceptance of my former Invitation of him into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> I shall be willing, after we have seen his Cathedral the Tower, to wait upon him up the Water to <hi>Lambeth;</hi> where his worthy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryman, the learned Mr. <hi>Colomiez,</hi> on my account, will condescend to let him into the <hi>Archives;</hi> upon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise, that he makes better use of the <hi>MSS.</hi> he sees there, than of those he calls <hi>Cardinal Bellay's;</hi> which are of so nice and so retir'd a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, that they will endure no visit from any other person besides Mr. <hi>Varillas:</hi> Of whom I shall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to observe at present, how little he understands of the Consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> whatever pretences he makes to be a Critick in the History of <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies,</hi> who takes Sir <hi>H. Spelman</hi> for a <hi>Calvinist,</hi> and thinks there is no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between <hi>Geneva</hi> and <hi>Great Britain.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:205509:30"/>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="reflection">
               <head>XX.</head>
               <p> But to proceed, <hi>Mr. Varillas tells us, that the aforesaid Council, held at</hi> London, <hi>forbid all Persons whatsoever to preach without permission from the Bishops.</hi> Farther he adds, <hi>That the Decisions of this Convocation at</hi> London, <hi>were inserted in a Decree of the Ʋniversity of</hi> Oxford, <hi>approv'd by</hi> Wicliff; <hi>which</hi> Spelman <hi>has also suppress'd, to put in its place a Piece, which can be manifestly convicted of Forgery, by the Testimony of</hi> Vington, <hi>an irreproachable Author in this matter.</hi> p. 43.]</p>
               <p n="1">1. I have so great a respect for the pious and worthy Sir <hi>H. Spelman,</hi> so basely handled by this Transcriber of <hi>Florimond,</hi> this Successour of <hi>Sorbier;</hi> not at all acquainted with the Character. of Books or Credit of Authors, that I cannot prevail with my self to discover how false the former part of this Paragraph is, till I have clear'd the latter. There has never been, perhaps, any Lay-man, that has so devoutly
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:205509:31"/>serv'd the Cause of his Mother the Church, as this incomparable Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman. He has not only display'd with Truth the former state of the <hi>English</hi> Church, but better'd the present, and has left a work, which if well considered, will do her justice, as to the rights of her Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony in after Ages. What can be said great of any man, that might not be said of him, who was so admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably learn'd, so judicious, so sincere, so pious, and in short, was every thing that Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> is not? Yet for all this, the <hi>Frenchman</hi> has been pleas'd to reflect upon him, as <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressing a certain decree of</hi> Oxford; which Animadversion betrays the Author not only not to have read the Book, as we observ'd before, but farther yet, not to have seen so much as the Title of it. For how absurd is it, to ask for a <hi>Censure</hi> of the <hi>Ʋniversity,</hi> in a work that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesses no more than a Collection of <hi>Church Constitutions;</hi> when by a
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:205509:31"/>parity of reason, he might as well fall upon the Author of the <hi>Oxford Antiquities,</hi> for omitting the relation of what has been acted in the <hi>Synods</hi> at <hi>London.</hi> And now to compare <hi>Vington</hi> (I suppose he means <hi>Knyghton</hi>) to Sir <hi>H. Spelman,</hi> shews who does it. What use he can pretend to make of <hi>Knyghton,</hi> is to me a Mystery; for in him nothing is seen of <hi>the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cisions of a Council of</hi> London, <hi>inserted in a Decree of the Ʋniversity of</hi> Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, <hi>approv'd by</hi> Wicliff. All that can be gathered from him, is, that <hi>Wicliff</hi> made a Recantation, there in full set down; which as yet only concerns the point of the Eucharist; so it is so far from being indeed a Recantation, that it is a free and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute Confession of that Faith which is now maintain'd in the Church of <hi>England;</hi> declaring, that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours body is <hi>verily and really pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent in the Sacrament,</hi> the Bread how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever retaining its proper Species. And I leave it even to Mr. <hi>Cockquelin</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:205509:32"/>to determine between us, whether that Man may be concluded to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce his opinion, the Opposers of which he brands with Heresie; and affirms, that at what time it was condemn'd by Authority, a Prodigy interven'd to deter the Judges from their unjust Proceedings. Neither would <hi>Tyssington</hi> and <hi>Winterton,</hi> and <hi>Wellys,</hi> and many more of his zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Adversaries have written pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posely against this Retractation, had it been so, and not rather a Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strance; which, because we submit the whole matter to the Readers judgment, we have affix'd at the end of these Papers from the Copy in <hi>Knyghton.</hi> Of whom, seeing Mr. <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillas</hi> has made mention, as an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor to be relied on in this matter, though in truth he was always an open enemy to <hi>Wicliffism;</hi> I desire leave to digress into a Quotation or two out of him, to shew the state of the <hi>Wicliffists</hi> in those days: In his Fifth Book he says, <hi>In those days
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:205509:32"/>this Sect was in great esteem, and so much increast in number that a man could not see Two people walking toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but One of them was a</hi> Wicliffist. And in another place, <hi>That that Party had gain'd half, or above half the Nation to their side.</hi> And these not Mechanicks, or the lowest sort of people, but, amongst them, <hi>many Knights,</hi> of whom he instances in some, <hi>and Dukes, and Earls. That since</hi> Wicliff <hi>had Translated the Bible, even the Women of that Profession un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood more than their Clergy did:</hi> For which he makes a long melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly Lamentation, and would fain perswade us, out of <hi>Gui de Sancto Amore,</hi> that <hi>Wicliff</hi> is indeed <hi>Anti-Christ.</hi> To whom, however, he has done so much justice in his cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, as to acknowledge him <hi>a most eminent Philosopher and Divine;</hi> and that <hi>as his Scholars always Foil'd their Adversaries in their Reasonings, so that he himself went beyond all Men of that Age in Disputing.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:205509:33"/>
               <p>Upon the whole matter, if my opinion were to be ask'd, whether this Annalist <hi>Monsieur Vington</hi> be so altogether <hi>irreproachable,</hi> not to take any notice how small a mans credit ought to be in his own Cause; I am affraid I should declare that to me he seem'd a Person of but a mild understanding, and a very narrow information. Otherwise, in these few leaves Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> pretends to have consulted, How could he have been so impos'd upon as to think that <hi>Wat Tyler</hi> and <hi>Jack Straw</hi> were one and the same man? How could he so forget himself as to call that in words at length <hi>The second year of King Richard,</hi> which by his own account, a little way of is the <hi>Fourth?</hi> Or lastly, why should he exclaim against a Preacher for this harmless remark, <hi>That amongst all the Prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes our Saviour made, he is never read to have gain'd a Priest?</hi> And all these things printed in his Works, out of a Manuscript thought to be
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:205509:33"/>of his own writing, by a person of unsuspected Integrity, Sir <hi>Roger Twisden,</hi> who has given us at the beginning of the Book the Authors own judgement of Himself;
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>"Me metuo dubium pro veris saepe locutum,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>"Plus audita loquor, quam mihi visa sequor.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q> Which ingenuous confession may serve indeed to attone for the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stakes of the well-meaning Canon; but will take away all pretences of excuse from Mr. <hi>Varillas,</hi> who with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out discretion embraces him as <hi>irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachable.</hi> 2. It remains that we speak something to the former part of this Paragraph; where we deny that in the <hi>London</hi>-Convocation held by <hi>Courtney</hi> 1382. Preaching with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Episcopal License was forbid: For in that Synod, it was only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solv'd that <hi>Hereford</hi> and <hi>Reppingdon,</hi> and <hi>Ayshton,</hi> should be silenc'd and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:205509:34"/>hindred from the Pulpit: But for any general Constitution to prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit all men whatever from Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without permission from the Ordinary, it was the Act of <hi>Th. Arundel,</hi> Successour to <hi>Courtney,</hi> in the See of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> who first procur'd it to be De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed. This may be seen in <hi>Lynwood</hi> and <hi>Athon,</hi> and
<note place="margin">(a) Dict. Theol. <hi>M. S.</hi> in Coll. Linc. Ox.</note>
                  <hi>Gascoign,</hi> famous Authors of the Century in which he liv'd. Nor are we bound to enquire if any of the little Writers have said the contrary, since 'tis the duty of an Historian not to take the advantage of any Authority, but to be restless till he has the best. In the late consus'd account of the Convocation, I had almost let pass without remark, an intrigue of the Duke of <hi>Lancasters,</hi> where he makes all the right of that Prince to the Kingdom of <hi>Castile,</hi> to proceed from <hi>an Excommunication of the King in possession, and a Donation of it to Duke</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:205509:34"/>John <hi>by the Pope, (p.</hi> 27. &amp; <hi>p.</hi> 40.) not knowing any thing of a propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety and just title he had acquired himself by his marriage with <hi>Constance,</hi> eldest Daughter to the Deceased King <hi>Piedro.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>XXI. To make our last observati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon what we have undertaken to consider: He relates <hi>the Death of</hi> Wicliff, <hi>which he represents as an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary act of God in striking him with a mortal Palsy, upon the Feast of St.</hi> Th. Becket, <hi>against whom he had prepared a Sermon for the Day.</hi> After that, <hi>he acquaints us, that his Scholars acknowledg'd him for a Saint, and attributed false miracles to him, till in the year</hi> 1486. <hi>Archbishop</hi> Arundel, <hi>in a Council at</hi> London, <hi>not content to condemn his Doctrines as before, did also burn his Books by the hand of the Hangman,</hi> p. 45, &amp;c.] 1. <hi>Thomas Becket</hi> is so well known, that no Loyal <hi>Englishman</hi> can believe Providence would interpose in savour of him, which is still the less proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:205509:35"/>at present, because our better Writers report this fit to have come upon <hi>Wicliff</hi> on the <hi>Festival of Holy Innocents,</hi> which is the day preceding. Dr. <hi>Gascoign,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">(b) In pag. ante Hist. Ivonis Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notens. M S. in Bibl. Cotton.</note> whose testimony about <hi>Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liff</hi> must be unquestionable, has in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd us, <hi>that having been troubled with a Palsy for two years before, it then became fatal to him;</hi> which in the decayed state of Old Age, after a life spent in action, and the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal heat now of course abated, can be no wonder. If the Monks were resolv'd not to let him dye without a Prodigy, it would have seem'd much more plausible and taking, had they inflicted upon him the Rickets, or the Small-pox. 2. If the Scholars of <hi>Wicliff</hi> thought him a Saint, and that he was assumed into Glory, they did but as became Men of Reason, and those who had been witnesses of the Sanctity of his Life, and Purity of his Doctrines.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:205509:35"/>But for what follows about <hi>the false Miracles,</hi> it is sheer invention; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi> very wary to mention any thing of that nature in the same page with <hi>Thomas of Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury:</hi> For <hi>Wicliff</hi>'s Followers made no <hi>Pilgrimages</hi> to <hi>Lutterworth,</hi> nor did they ever turn up the Cloaks of their Adversaries to look for their <hi>Tails.</hi> 3. As to the business of <hi>Arundel,</hi> and the <hi>burning of the books,</hi> which in words, at length, he makes to be done in the year 1486. it is impossible to be reconcil'd to truth: That action in reality fell out about the year 1410, so we are willing to think Mr. <hi>Varillas</hi>'s Pen has slipt, and by chance mistaken a hundred years, and that he meant to ascribe it to <hi>Ann. Dom.</hi> 1386. because, (in <hi>p.</hi> 42.) he tells us, <hi>that in the preced<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing year</hi> 1385 Courtney <hi>died, and</hi> Arundel <hi>succeeded in the Archbisho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prick of</hi> Canterbury: Which how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is notoriously false; For <hi>Courtney</hi> died not till <hi>July</hi> 31. 1396. (unless
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:205509:36"/>he died twice, in imitation of his Predecessour <hi>Sudbury</hi>) and the same Year, about <hi>Christmas,</hi> was <hi>Arun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del</hi> translated to <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have at last, not without great violence us'd upon my inclination, pass't through what relates to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in the First Book of Mr. <hi>Varillas;</hi> and I think I may have deserv'd as many Livres for my Patience, as He has had for his Invention. If nothing will perswade him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce his Pen and Ink, but he has sworn still to go on writing Legends, to the utter destruction of Monsieur <hi>Barbin</hi> and his Family, and to the everlasting disgrace of Mr. <hi>Cocquelin;</hi> and in the mean time is willing to continue his Scene in <hi>England,</hi> I shall take the boldness to recommend to his Fancy the renowned Story of the Ten thousand <hi>Ʋrsulins,</hi> which at present labours under a few incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences, and is not so well receiv'd as it deserves, by some Scrupulous Hereticks. For the Truth of what
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:205509:36"/>He shall say, I confess I am not able to help him to any such Manuscripts as he commonly makes use of; but in lieu, I can tell him where at a very cheap rate he may furnish himself with Witnesses. But to let him know in truth what the World thinks of him: He has writ away all his Credit; his last defence of himself has prov'd him Inexcusable, and made men apt to think that as in <hi>England</hi> at present, so in <hi>France</hi> too, the same person that is Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riographer, is also Laureat: Hence it might be, that <hi>Monsieur Varillas</hi> in his Revolutions, takes all the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of a Poet, and Mr. <hi>Dr</hi>— in his Conference between the <hi>Hind and Panther,</hi> tho in Verse, has aim'd at all the plainness and gravity of an Historian.</p>
               <p>For History is indeed a serious mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, not to be written carelessly like a Letter to a Friend, nor with <hi>Passion,</hi> like a Billet to a Mistress; nor with <hi>Biass,</hi> like a Declamation for a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:205509:37"/>at the Bar, or the Remonstrance of a Minister for his Prince; nor in fine, by a man unacquainted with the World, like Soliloquies and Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. It requires a long Experience, a sound Judgement, a close Attention, an unquestionable Integrity, and a style without Affectation: All which glorious accomplishments, as they are wanting in the Author of <hi>The Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in Matters of Religion,</hi> so there is no Historian that I know of, in whom they have shew'd themselves to so high and admirable a degree, as in a Physician of our Age, who has ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd the World with a <hi>History of Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases;</hi> and whose Name is too great to mention in a Pamphlet of this Character.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div xml:lang="mne" type="appendix">
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:205509:37"/>
            <head>The Belief of Dr. <hi>John Wicliff,</hi> in the point of the <hi>Eucharist,</hi> which by heedless Men has been call'd his Recantation.</head>
            <p>WE beleve as Crist and his Apostolus han tauʒt us, that the Sacrament of the Auter white and ronde and like tyl oure brede or ost unsacrede is verray Goddus body in fourme of brede, and if it be broken in thre parties os the Kirke uses, or elles in a thousand, everlky one of these parties is the same Godus body, and right so as the persone of Crist is verray God and verray man, verray Godhede and verray manhede ryth so as holy Kyrk many hundrrith wynter has trowyde, the same Sacrament is verray Godus body and verray brede: os it is forme of Goddus body and form of brede as techith Crist and his Apostolus. And therefore seynt Poule nemyth it never but whan he callus it bred,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:205509:38"/> and he be oure beleve tok his wit of God in this: and the argument of heretykus agayne this sentens, lyth to a christene man for to assolve. And right as it is heresie for to trowe that this Sacrament is Goddus body and no brede, for it is bothe togedur. But the most heresie that God sufferide come tyl his Kyrke, is to trowe that this Sacrament is an accident with a substance and may on no wise be Goddus body: for Crist sayde be witnesse of Iohn, that this brede is my body, and if the say that be this skylle that holy Kyrke hat bene in heresie many hundred wynter, sothe it is, spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially sythen the fende was lousede that was be wittnesse of Angele to Iohn Evaungeliste aftur a thousande wynter that Crist was stenenyde to heven. But it is to suppose that many seyntes that dyede in the mene time before her detz were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of this erroure. Owe howe
<unclear>grete</unclear> diversite is betwene us that
<unclear>trowes</unclear> that this Sacrament is verray brede in his kynde, and <unclear>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuene</unclear> heretykus that tell us that
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:205509:38"/> this an accident with outen a sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecte. For before that the fende fader of Iesyngus was lowside, was never this gabbing contryvede. And howe grete diversite is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene us that trowes that this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament that in his kynde is verray brede and sacramentally Goddus body, and betwe heretykes that trowes and telles that this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may on none wyse be God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus body. For I dar sewrly say that ʒif this were soth, Crist and his seynts dyede heretykus, and the more partye of holy Kyrke bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vyth nowe heresie, and before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voute men suppos ene that this consayle of Freres and London was with the hery dene. For they put an heresie up on Crist and seynts in hevyne: wherefore the erthe tremblide fayland maynnus voys ansueryde for God als it dide in tyme of his passion whan he was dambnyde to bodely deth. Crist and his modur that in gronde had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyde alle heresyes kepe his Kyrke in right beleve of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and wene the king and his rewme to ask sharply of his clerkus
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:205509:39"/> this offis that alle his possessioners on paine of lesyng of alle her tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poraltes telle the king and his rewme with sufficient grownding, what is this Sacrament, and alle the orders of Freres on paine of leysing of her legians telle the king and his rewme with gode grounding what is the Sacrament. For I am cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the thridde partie of clergie that defendus thise doutes that is here saide, that they will defende it on paine of her lyf.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>In p.</hi> 5. <hi>for</hi> Polydore Virgil <hi>read</hi> Harpsfield.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:205509:39"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>